Guide to the Joel Raphaelson papers, 1950-2019 and undated RL.01070
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Joel Raphaelson papers
1950-2019 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Raphaelson, Joel
RL.01070
4.8 Linear Feet
Joel Raphaelson was an advertising executive with Ogilvy & Mather in New York and Chicago. The Joel Raphaelson papers include correspondence, speeches and presentations, writing drafts and other printed materials as well as audiovisual materials in multiple formats (videocassettes, optical disks, audio reels). Topics include agency and account management, management philosophy and strategic direction, and theories of writing for business and advertising copy. A significant portion of the collection is devoted to correspondence with David Ogilvy, Ogilvy's memos and other writings. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Access Restrictions
Access restricted.
Provenance
The Joel Raphaelson papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2007 and 2019
Biographical / Historical Note
Joel Raphaelson was an advertising executive with Ogilvy & Mather in New York and Chicago. Raphaelson was born in New York in 1928 and attended Harvard University (BA, 1949). He worked as a copywriter at BBDO (approximately 1953-1958) before joining Ogilvy & Mather as copywriter in 1958. Raphaelson became Executive Creative Director of the Ogilvy Chicago office when it opened in 1976 and from around 1982 edited and published various Ogilvy & Mather publications (Magic Lanterns, Viewpoint), and served as Senior Vice President for International Creative Services. He retired in 1995.
Collection Overview
The Joel Raphaelson papers include correspondence, speeches and presentations, writing drafts and other printed materials as well as audiovisual materials in multiple formats (videocassettes, optical disks, audio reels). Topics include agency and account management, management philosophy and strategic direction, and theories of writing for business and advertising copy. A significant portion of the collection is devoted to correspondence with David Ogilvy, Ogilvy's memos and other writings. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Related Materials
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center collections:
David B. McCall papers
J. Walter Thompson Company. Rena Bartos papers
Jock Elliott papers
John R. Blaney papers
Kenneth Roman papers
William R. Phillips papers
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: General Files; Printed Materials; Speeches, Writings, Presentations; Audiovisual Materials.
Color slides; Audiotapes; Publications; Videotapes; Advertising -- United States -- History; Advertising agencies; Advertising agencies -- Management; Advertising executives -- United States; Ogilvy & Mather; Ogilvy, David, 1911-1999; Raphaelson, Joel; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
- General Files, 1950-2019 and undated; 1
  - Biographical information, 1991-2019 (Box 1)
  - Biographical information (clippings), 1977-1986 (Box 10)
  - Chronological files, 1950-1984; 8 folders (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes correspondence with David Ogilvy and others; print advertisements, attachments and other materials
  - Chronological files, 1957-1992; 5 folders (Box 10)
  - Chronological files, 1979-1992; 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Chronological files (English, French, German), 1979-1991; 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Chronological files, 1985-1987; 7 folders (Box 2)
  - Chronological files, 1989-1991; 6 folders (Box 3)
  - Chronological files, 1991-1999; 6 folders (Box 4)
  - Correspondence--David Ogilvy, Magic Lanterns, 1976-1982 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence--David Ogilvy, Magic Lanterns, 1976-1982 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence--European assignment, 1975-1976 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence--How to Be a Good Creative Director, 1980-1985 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence--Jock Elliott, 1967-1990 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence--Miscellaneous, 1965-1991 and undated; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Correspondence--University of Texas, Austin, 1989-1991 (Box 5)
- Printed Material, 1953-2012 and undated; 2
  - Ogilvy & Mather, 1955-1994 and undated; 1
    - Annual reports, 1967, 1972 (Box 5)
    - Chicago--Keyline newsletter, 1981 (Box 5)
    - Chicago--Report on the first five years, 1981 (Box 10)
    - Directory of Services and Sources, 1986 (Box 5)
    - Dove print advertisements, 1955 (Oversize-folder 1)
    - Flagbearer, 1960-1989 (Box 5)
    - How to Run an Ogilvy & Mather Agency (Andrew Kershaw, Paul Biklen), 1977 (Box 6)
    - How to Write Better (Ken Roman, Joel Raphaelson), 1978 (Box 6)
    - International Bulletin, 1975 (Box 6)
    - Making Red Redder (credentials book), 1994 (Box 11)
    - Networking newsletter, undated (Box 6)
    - Off the Wall (sayings collected for William Phillips retirement), 1989 (Box 6)
    - Principles of Account Management (William Phillips), undated (Box 6)
    - Speeches and Suits (William Phillips), 1988 (Box 6)
    - Staff meeting reports, 1966-1973 (Box 6)
    - The Idea, undated (Box 10)
    - The People Book, 1985 (Box 6)
    - There Is Nothing New About Change (Norman Berry), 1988 (Box 6)
    - Viewpoint, 1994 Dec. (Box 6)
    - Who We Are--And Where We're Not Going (Ken Roman), 1988 (Box 6)
    - Young, Ambitious Men Can Move Fast and Far at Ogilvy & Mather, 1968 (Box 6)
  - Other Sources, 1953-2012 and undated; 2
    - American Institute of Men's and Boys' Wear--Dress Right campaign booklet, 1957 (Box 6)
    - Bart Cummings--The Benelovent Dictators (segment on David Ogilvy), 1982 (Box 6)
    - Batten, Barton, Durstine & Osborn (BBDO)--Print advertisements, 1953-1958; 2 folders (Box 12)
      Copy by Joel Raphaelson; includes DuPont, New York Times, American Institute of Men's and Boys' Wear
    - Batten, Barton, Durstine & Osborn (BBDO)--Print advertisements (DuPont), 1956 (Oversize-folder 1)
      Copy by Joel Raphaelson
    - David Ogilvy--Growth with Present Clients Is the Healthiest Form of Growth, undated (Box 6)
    - David Ogilvy--Principles of Management, 1968-1970 (Box 6)
    - Dorothy Sarnoff--Speech Dynamics, 1992 (Box 6)
    - Founding Fathers of Advertising Research (interviews with Rena Bartos, Arthur Pearson), 1977 (Box 6)
    - General Baking/Bond Bread--Business to business advertisement, 1956 (Box 6)
    - How to Create More Effective Radio Advertising--Joel Raphaelson talk announcement, 1979 (Box 6)
    - Ken Roman, Joel Raphaelson--Writing that Works, 2000 (Box 6)
    - Mather & Crowther--The Creative Concept (Stanhope Shelton), 1964 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous print advertisements by others, 1940s-1984 (Box 12)
      Includes: American Airlines, American Tobacco (BBDO), European Health Spas, Life Savers, Lucky Strike (BBDO), Riteway
    - Rums of Puerto Rico--Print advertisement with letter to the advertiser, undated (Box 10)
    - The Unpublished Davig Ogilvy (uncorrected edition), 2012 (1986) (Box 6)
- Writings, Speeches, Presentations, 1954-1999 and undated; 3
  - David Ogilvy, 1954-1993 and undated; 3
    - 15 Bees in My Bonnet, 1993 (Box 7)
    - Annual Advertising Awards, 1954 (Box 7)
    - Creative Council/Touffou circulars index, 1978-1981 (Box 7)
    - Creative Council memos, 1976-1980 (Box 7)
    - David Ogilvy project transcripts, 1987; 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Does Advertising Deserve Its Reputation? (Open Mind panel), 1962 (Box 7)
    - How to Lead a Creative Organization, undated (Box 7)
    - How to Raise the Creative Standards of Ogilvy & Mather, 1990 (Box 7)
    - New Business Policies of OBM, undated (Box 7)
    - Research on Advertising Techniques that Work--And Don't Work (with Joel Raphaelson), 1982 (Box 7)
    - Speech to Direct Mail Advertising Association (DMAA), 1963 (Box 7)
    - Speech to life insurance agency management (on direct mail), 1965 (Box 7)
    - The Leo Burnett I Knew, 1991 (Box 7)
    - Touffou memos, 1980-1983 (Box 7)
    - View from Touffou, undated (Box 7)
    - Views on various subjects (index), undated (Box 7)
    - We Sell--Or Else!, 1991 (Box 7)
  - Jock Elliott, 1964-1994 and undated; 4
    - Advanced Management Program, 1979 (Box 8)
    - Advertising Hall of Fame acceptance, 1984 (Box 8)
    - American Jewish Committee, 1978 (Box 8)
    - American Marketing Association, 1980 (Box 8)
    - Analysts meeting, 1979 (Box 8)
    - Bob Keim roast, undated (Box 8)
    - Clio Awards, 1981 (Box 8)
    - Denver Advertising Federation, 1987 (Box 8)
    - Flag Day, 1988 (Box 8)
    - How Far Can You Stretch Your Coffee Break?, 1972 (Box 8)
    - How to Be Successful and Happy in the Advertising Business, 1994 (Box 8)
    - In Memory of Andrew Kershaw, 1978 (Box 8)
    - Joint talk (with Elly Elliott) to International House, 1987 (Box 8)
    - Magazine Publishers Association, 1974 (Box 8)
    - New Year's Pome, 1992 (Box 8)
    - Outlook for Advertising in a Restrictive Economy, 1974 (Box 8)
    - Parking Problem, undated (Box 8)
    - Presentation to the financial community of New York, 1978 (Box 8)
    - Presentation to the New York Society of Security Analysts, 1969 (Box 8)
    - Progress report on O&M affirmative action program, 1968 (Box 8)
    - Pros and Cons of the Fee System, 1964 (Box 8)
    - Public Service Advertising, 1986 (Box 8)
    - Public Service Advertising in the United States, 1985 (Box 8)
    - Re-Skilling Britain, 1987 (Box 8)
    - Reader's Digest, 1986 (Box 8)
    - Shareholders' meeting, 1979 (Box 8)
    - Some Do's and Don't's About Public Service Advertising, 1988 (Box 8)
    - Staff meeting, 1981 (Box 8)
    - Talk to Delhi staff, 1978 (Box 8)
    - Talk to London staff, 1978 (Box 8)
    - Talk to OBM staff, 1965 (Box 8)
    - United Jewish Appeal, 1981 (Box 8)
    - Western Region, American Advertising Federation (AAF), 1987 (Box 8)
    - What (Gloomy) Gus Says and What I Say Back, 1975 (Box 8)
    - Why Don't You Speak for Yourself, John?, 1981 (Box 8)
    - Wouldn't It Be Better If--?, 1974 (Box 8)
  - Joel Raphaelson, 1975-1999 and undated; 5
    - Big Ideas, 1981 (Box 8)
    - How Do You Know?, 1999 (Box 8)
    - How to Evaluate Radio Commercials, undated (Box 8)
    - Interview with David Ogilvy, 1986-1987 (Box 8)
    - Lesson One from David Ogilvy, 1983 (Box 9)
    - Little Differences that Make a Big Difference on TV, 1988 (Box 9)
    - Rescue that Campaign!, 1975-1976 (Box 9)
    - Secret About Copywriters, undated (Box 9)
    - Suggestions for Making Better Radio Commercials, 1976 (Box 9)
    - What Do They Want? What Will They Pay For?, 1993 (Box 9)
    - Writing for Results, 1990 (Box 9)
  - Other Sources, 1974-1991 and undated; 6
    - Andrew Byrne--The Purpose of Advertising Is Increased Sales, 1980 (Box 9)
    - Andrew Ehrenberg--Repetitive Advertising and the Consumer, 1974 (Box 10)
    - Graham Phillips--The View from the Bridge on Client Services, 1991 (Box 9)
    - Henry Bernhard--A Look Before We Leap into the 1980s, 1979 (Box 9)
    - Unattributed--Why O&M Should Advertise, and How, undated (Box 9)
- Audiovisual Materials, 1982-2011 and undated; 4
  - Joel Raphaelson's 30th O&M Anniversary, 1988 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL01070-VHS-001)
    Includes: Bill Whitney; Who's Marikay?
  - Ogilvy & Mather "Little Differences" reel 13:00, undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL01070-VHS-002)
  - Ogilvy & Mather Magic Lanterns, David Ogilvy intro 12:00, 1986 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL01070-VHS-003)
  - Ogilvy & Mather Direct, David Ogilvy presentation 7:00, 1988 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL01070-VHS-004)
  - Reflections on David Ogilvy with Joel Raphaelson 42:00, undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL01070-VHS-005)
  - Leo Burnett: When to Take My Name Off the Door, undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL01070-Umatic-001)
  - Ogilvy & Mather commercial compilation, undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL01070-Umatic-002)
    Includes: Perking Pot; Horse and Wagon (apple turnover); Statues; William Miller; Rags to Riches
  - Ogilvy & Mather "Little Differences That Make a Big Difference" TV examples only, 1992 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL01070-Umatic-003)
    Includes: 2 AT&T spots; Biker; Mary Ryan; Sports Illustrated; Amex; Joe Sedelmeier; Pavarotti; Super Glue; Hallmark
  - Pesky rules speech, commercials reel, undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL01070-Umatic-004)
    Includes: Miller Lite; American Express, Landry; Rave, Six Years Old; Fed Ex, Fast Pace; Mistral; Diet Rite; Pavarotti; Rheems; Xerox
  - Ogilvy & Mather and Chicago, 2011 (Box AV1, Video-disc RL01070-OP-001)
  - Ogilvy & Mather: Joel's Remembrances of Hank Bernhard, 2011 (Box AV1, Video-disc RL01070-OP-002)
  - Ogilvy & Mather: Joel's Remembrances of Hank Bernhard, 2011 (Box AV1, Video-disc RL01070-OP-003)
  - Radio Freak, current reel, 1982 (Box AV1, Audio-reel RL01070-RR-001)
  - Radio Freak, original presentation, 17:00, undated (Box AV1, Audio-reel RL01070-RR-002)